Hi.
This is the first lecture
in MIT's course 18.06,
linear algebra, and
I'm Gilbert Strang.
The text for the
course is this book,
Introduction to Linear Algebra.
And the course web page, which
has got a lot of exercises from
the past, MatLab codes, the
syllabus for the course,
is web.mit.edu/18.06.
And this is the first
lecture, lecture one.
So, and later we'll give the
web address for viewing these,
videotapes.
Okay, so what's in
the first lecture?
This is my plan.
The fundamental problem
of linear algebra,
which is to solve a system
of linear equations.
So let's start
with a case when we
have some number of equations,
say n equations and n unknowns.
So an equal number of
equations and unknowns.
That's the normal, nice case.
And what I want to do is --
with examples, of course --
to describe, first, what
I call the Row picture.
That's the picture of
one equation at a time.
It's the picture you've
seen before in two
by two equations
where lines meet.
So in a minute, you'll
see lines meeting.
The second picture,
I'll put a star
beside that, because that's
such an important one.
And maybe new to you is the
picture -- a column at a time.
And those are the rows
and columns of a matrix.
So the third -- the algebra
way to look at the problem is
the matrix form and using
a matrix that I'll call A.
Okay, so can I do an example?
The whole semester will be
examples and then see what's
going on with the example.
So, take an example.
Two equations, two unknowns.
So let me take 2x
-y =0, let's say.
And -x 2y=3.
Okay.
let me -- I can even
say right away --
what's the matrix, that is,
what's the coefficient matrix?
The matrix that involves
these numbers --
a matrix is just a
rectangular array of numbers.
Here it's two rows and
two columns, so 2 and --
minus 1 in the first row minus
1 and 2 in the second row,
that's the matrix.
And the right-hand
-- the, unknown --
well, we've got two unknowns.
So we've got a vector, with
two components, x and y,
and we've got two right-hand
sides that go into a vector
0 3.
I couldn't resist writing
the matrix form, right --
even before the pictures.
So I always will think
of this as the matrix A,
the matrix of coefficients,
then there's a vector of
unknowns.
Here we've only
got two unknowns.
Later we'll have any
number of unknowns.
And that vector of
unknowns, well I'll often --
I'll make that x --
extra bold.
A and the right-hand
side is also a vector
that I'll always call b.
So linear equations are A
x equal b and the idea now
is to solve this
particular example
and then step back to
see the bigger picture.
Okay, what's the picture for
this example, the Row picture?
Okay, so here comes
the Row picture.
So that means I take
one row at a time
and I'm drawing
here the xy plane
and I'm going to plot
all the points that
satisfy that first equation.
So I'm looking at all the
points that satisfy 2x-y =0.
It's often good to start with
which point on the horizontal
line -- on this horizontal
line, y is zero.
The x axis has y as zero and
that -- in this case, actually,
then x is zero.
So the point, the origin --
the point with coordinates
(0,0) is on the line.
It solves that equation.
Okay, tell me in -- well,
I guess I have to tell you
another point that solves
this same equation.
Let me suppose x is one,
so I'll take x to be one.
Then y should be two, right?
So there's the point one two
that also solves this equation.
And I could put in more points.
But, but let me put
in all the points
at once, because they all
lie on a straight line.
This is a linear equation
and that word linear
got the letters
Okay, thanks. for line in it.
That's the equation --
this is the line that ...
of solutions to 2x-y=0 my
first row, first equation.
So typically, maybe, x equal
a half, y equal one will work.
And sure enough it does.
Okay, that's the first one.
Now the second one is not
going to go through the origin.
It's always important.
Do we go through
the origin or not?
In this case, yes, because
there's a zero over there.
In this case we don't
go through the origin,
because if x and y are
zero, we don't get three.
So, let me again say
suppose y is zero,
what x do we actually get?
If y is zero, then I
get x is minus three.
So if y is zero, I
go along minus three.
So there's one point
on this second line.
Now let me say, well,
suppose x is minus one --
just to take another x.
If x is minus one,
then this is a one
and I think y should be a one,
because if x is minus one,
then I think y should be a
one and we'll get that point.
Is that right?
If x is minus one, that's a one.
If y is a one, that's
a two and the one
and the two make three and
that point's on the equation.
Okay.
Now, I should just
draw the line, right,
connecting those
two points at --
that will give me
the whole line.
And if I've done
this reasonably well,
I think it's going to happen
to go through -- well,
not happen -- it was arranged
to go through that point.
So I think that the
second line is this one,
and this is the all-important
point that lies on both lines.
Shall we just check
that that point which
is the point x equal one
and y was two, right?
That's the point there
and that, I believe,
solves both equations.
Let's just check this.
If x is one, I have a minus one
plus four equals three, okay.
Apologies for
drawing this picture
that you've seen before.
But this -- seeing
the row picture --
first of all, for n equal 2,
two equations and two unknowns,
it's the right place to start.
Okay.
So we've got the solution.
The point that
lies on both lines.
Now can I come to
the column picture?
Pay attention, this
is the key point.
So the column picture.
I'm now going to look at
the columns of the matrix.
I'm going to look at
this part and this part.
I'm going to say that the
x part is really x times --
you see, I'm putting the two --
I'm kind of getting the
two equations at once --
that part and then I have a
y and in the first equation
it's multiplying a minus one and
in the second equation a two,
and on the right-hand
side, zero and three.
You see, the columns of the
matrix, the columns of A
are here and the
right-hand side b is there.
And now what is the
equation asking for?
It's asking us to find --
somehow to combine that vector
and this one in the right
amounts to get that one.
It's asking us to find the
right linear combination --
this is called a
linear combination.
And it's the most fundamental
operation in the whole course.
It's a linear combination
of the columns.
That's what we're
seeing on the left side.
Again, I don't want to
write down a big definition.
You can see what it is.
There's column one,
there's column two.
I multiply by some
numbers and I add.
That's a combination -- a linear
combination and I want to make
those numbers the right
numbers to produce zero three.
Okay.
Now I want to draw a picture
that, represents what this --
this is algebra.
What's the geometry, what's
the picture that goes with it?
Okay.
So again, these vectors
have two components,
so I better draw a
picture like that.
So can I put down these columns?
I'll draw these
columns as they are,
and then I'll do a
combination of them.
So the first column is over
two and down one, right?
So there's the first column.
The first column.
Column one.
It's the vector two minus one.
The second column is --
minus one is the first
component and up two.
It's here.
There's column two.
So this, again, you see
what its components are.
Its components are
minus one, two.
Good.
That's this guy.
Now I have to take
a combination.
What combination shall I take?
Why not the right
combination, what the hell?
Okay.
So the combination
I'm going to take
is the right one to
produce zero three
and then we'll see it
happen in the picture.
So the right combination is
to take x as one of those